R. Todd Stephens, Ph.D.

210 Harris Rd

Fayetteville, GA 30215 Email: todd@rtodd.com

Summary

Thirty years of experience in Architectural Design, System/Department Leadership, Collaboration Technologies and Business Integration provides a unique opportunity to bring in one with the technical expertise and the business knowledge that is needed by today's information technology professional. Proficient in prioritizing and completing tasks in a timely manner, yet flexible to multitask when necessary. Customer focused with diverse industry experience including telecommunications, retail, manufacturing, and software development.

Qualifications

Thirty plus years of Information Systems experience, qualified by extensive senior level experience in:

- Human Computer Interaction
- Architecture Roadmaps
- Marketing IT Strategy
- Enterprise Metadata Strategy
- Social Media Strategy
- Cloud Computing Technology
- Collaboration Strategy
- Information Visualization
- Advanced Presentation Skills
- Department Leadership
- Human Capital Development
- Internet / Intranet Development

Experience

Senior Technical Architect Lead System Analyst Senior Systems Technologist Asst. MIS Manager Senior Programmer Analyst Senior Programmer Analyst Assistant Vice President

AT&T Corporation
Georgia Pacific Corporation
The Coca-Cola Company ©
Southern Linen
Fannie Mae Software Systems
Lummus Industries
The Georgia Company

August 1997 - Present February 1996 - August 1997 August 1990 - February 1996 June 1989 - August 1990 March 1989 - June 1989 June 1988 - March 1989 February 1983 - June 1988

© Consultant Position

Education

Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.)

Major: Information Systems GPA: 3.89

Masters in Business Administration (MBA)

Major: Information Systems Management GPA: 3.45

Bachelor of Science (BS)

Major: Math. Science / Computer Science GPA: 3.12

Nova Southeastern University
Upsilon Pi Epsilon Honorary Society

Georgia State University

Major: 3.75

Columbus State University

Honors: Deans List

Technical Skills

- Knowledge Management
- Social Media Applications
- Data / Information Architecture
- Technical Architecture
- Web Design and Usability
- Video Technologies
- Taxonomy Development
- HTML, JavaScript, JQuery
- MS FrontPage / WebMatrix
- Sharepoint Designer

- Enterprise Architecture
- MS-Project, ABT Workbench
- MS Office Products
- MS Sharepoint (WSS/MOSS)
- Visual Studio

E-Mail: todd@rtodd.com References available upon Request

Selected Achievements

Communications and Design

Initiated a communication strategy for an Enterprise Cloud Computing program which included the cloud service catalog, cloud communications portal, and a social media campaign. Additionally, I managed a virtual team of content providers for education material which also included a monthly newsletter, metric dashboards and training. **Results**: The cloud program has taken off with over 100,000 visit to the portal and over 800 members to the social community. The communications and marketing has contributed hugely to the success of the overall program.

Enterprise Architecture

Architected and Designed the "Enterprise Metadata Strategy" solution for BellSouth. Strategy not only focused on the database assets but the entire architecture portfolio: patterns, frameworks, schemas, components, web services, documents, open source, etc. This effort established BellSouth as the standard for Asset Lifecycle Management in the industry as well as defining the foundation to move to the next level of maturity.

Results: The entire asset base has cataloged which enables numerous programs around governance, reuse, and new architectures (Extensible). The asset collection totaled over 167,000 built for reuse and enabling SOA architectures.

Additional Enterprise Architecture Efforts

- Establishment of an Enterprise Data Architecture
- Establishment of an Enterprise Extensible Architecture
- Automation and End-to-End Procurement of the Standard Operating Environment (SOE)
- Establishment of a Corporate Governance Process for Reusable Assets

Collaboration and Online Services

In 2005, our organization was approached to **enable** the information worker portfolio of tools to the BellSouth/AT&T communities. Our approach was to focus on the customer and develop services and solutions to match the product offering of the architecture community.

Results: Collaborative environments went from 200 to 4,500 in 20 months. As of 2009, we had enabled over 80,000 collaborative environments as well as deployed the enterprise social software. Both the business and technology communities embraced the technology and transformed it into real business value.

Business Integration

Designed and Implemented an online ordering system that redesigned internal ordering, cataloging, order management, and financial integration. The system processed \$21 million dollars worth orders in the first 12 months.

Results: The systems had a positive ROI in the first 6 months; eventually saving the organization \$3 million a year in cost savings. When Hurricane Katrina hit, the system was able to process the infrastructure orders in weeks instead of four months; enabling the complete replacement of infrastructure within a month. The application is now moving to extend the enterprise architecture into the fourth level of maturity by automating the end to end processing of products, standards, and configuration management.

Additional Information

Sixteen Issued United States Patents

Over 150 professional and academic publications within Information Technology

Selected as one of top four "Best Practices" Metadata implementations in 2002 and 2003

Authored Book: Trademark 2.0 (Top 1% on Amazon, June 2007)

Co-Author on Eleven Academic Books on SOA, Open Source, Web 2.0, Collaboration, and Knowledge Mgt. Adjunct Professor at LaGrange College (2004-2005)

Track Chair for several Academic Conferences and Editorial Board for Business Journal

MCTS: Microsoft Office SharePoint Server 2007, MCTS: Windows SharePoint Services 3.0

Nano-Degree Certification (12 Months): iOS Development: Expected 2016